Today's דף daf. *daf* is קל״א *kuf lamed aleph*, 131. We pick
up on the bottom of ק״ל *kuf lamed*. We are discussing here,
since we're talking about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*'s position, that
מכשירי מילה machshirei milah *machshirei milah* can be done on שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbos*. Even things preparatory to the ברית מילה bris milah. *bris milah*
can override שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. And we discussed the case about carrying
a knife through courtyards and so on, where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
clearly said that doesn't, that's not רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*.
That could have even been done in a totally permissible way, because
even if you don't make an עירובי חצרות chatzerot *eruvei chatzeros* and
so on, all the courtyards, according to at least the position of
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, could be considered to be one domain and
you can carry from one end to the other because they are
surrounded by sufficient walls. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* introduces a
somewhat strange statement, which seems to argue, but we'll see what the
context is. We'll pick it up, we ended it with yesterday about
ten lines from the bottom of ק״ל *kuf lamed* עמוד amud. ב
*amud beis*. איתמר *itmar*, it was taught, אמר רבי זירא אמר רב
*amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav*: מבוי mavoi שלא נשתתפו בו, אין מטלטלין
בו אלא ella, בארבע אמות *mavoi shelo nishtatfu bo, ein metalatlin bo
ela bearba amos*. A מבוי mavoi, *mavoi* that you did not make
a שיתוף shituf *shittuf*, again a מבוי mavoi, *mavoi* is an alleyway
that the courtyards open up to, and if the courtyards themselves did
not join together, which is normally what you want to do if
you want to carry in the alleyway, the same way the houses
joined in the courtyard in one, let's say, in some loaves of
bread. So the courtyards joined together though to be considered one domain
with the alleyway that they're all together. If they did not do
this, אין מטלטלין בו אלא ela בארבע אמות *ein metalatlin bo ela
bearba amos*, you can only carry in that courtyard, in that alleyway,
within four אמות *amos*, meaning you can't carry in it.
And presumably even if something starts in that courtyard, which is different
than we said before about the חצר chatzer *chatzer* and the roofs
and so on. אמר אביי, Abaye: היי מילתא אמרה רבי זירא ולא
פירשה *amar Abaye, hai milta amrah Rabbi Zeira velo perashah*. אביי Abaye
*Abaye* said, רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* said this, but he never explained
it, עד דאתא רבה בר אבוה ופירשה *ad de'ata Rabbah bar Avuha
uperashah*, until רבה בר אבוה *Rabbah bar Avuha* came along and explained
it. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב *amar Rav
Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar Rav*: מבוי mavoi. שלא נשתתפו בו
*mavoi shelo nishtatfu bo*, if again you have this מבוי mavoi. *mavoi*
that the courtyards did not combine into,
you know, sort of partner into, עירבו חצרות chatzerot. עם בתים *eirvu
chatzeros im battim*. So here's the ironic statement: if the courtyards had
their own עירוב eruv *eiruv* together with their houses, of the courtyards,
which is a first step in the right direction, אין מטלטלין בו
אלא ela בארבע אמות *ein metalatlin bo ela bearba amos*. Then the
alleyway is off-limits. You can only carry in four אמות *amos*. Again,
this is for things that start in the alleyway, and remember it's
surrounded by walls.
I mean, whatever it's surrounded by, the walls make the houses. The
houses make the walls. לא עירבו חצרות chatzerot עם בתים *lo eirvu
chatzeros im battim*, if you didn't even start doing the right thing,
that the courtyards and the houses did not combine in their local
עירובים *eiruvim*, then מותר לטלטל בכולו *muttar letaltel bekulo*, you can carry
in the alleyway for things that start in it. So, quite paradoxical.
So let's see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explains it. אמר ליה
רב חנינא חוזאה לרבא *amar lei Rav Chanina Chuza'ah leRava*. רב חנינא
חוזאה *Rav Chanina Chuza'ah* says to רבא *Rava*: מאי שנא כי עירבו
חצרות chatzerot עם בתים דנידקו חצרות chatzerot ונעשו בתים *mai shena ki
eirvu chatzeros im battim denidku chatzeros vena'asu battim*. So he understands the
first part of it. He says: I get why, when the houses
made an עירוב eruv *eiruv* in their local courtyards, why that makes
the alleyway off-limits. Why, although it seems a paradox? Because of the
following reason: דנידקו חצרות chatzeros, ונעשו בתים *denidku chatzeros vena'asu battim*. The
חצרות chatzeros *chatzeros* have been sort of like uprooted and they've been
made like houses. Since now you can carry in the courtyards, and
because the whole, each courtyard is considered rather than to be a
domain for multiple different houses, the whole idea of an עירוב eruv,
*eiruv*, of a joining together in a loaf of bread, is the
following: is that you have multiple houses that open into a courtyard,
even though technically it's a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid? *reshus hayachid* in
the sense that it's surrounded by walls, but every house is a
different domain and the courtyard has equal use of all the various
houses in it. So in terms of ownership and use, at that
experiential level, they're different domains. It's not all one single domain. So
the idea of joining together, of doing an עירובי חצרות *eruvei chatzeros*
in like a loaf of bread, is that you make it as
if it's all one unified domain, okay? And it's all owned presumably
like by one person, whoever's holding onto the loaf of bread. So
he says: okay, so if you did that in each individual courtyard,
then each individual courtyard stops, at least within this fiction, of being
a courtyard, and it becomes essentially like a house. Each courtyard becomes
a single person's domain. So now, okay, so, okay fine, but at
least it lets you carry. Ah, but if that's true, ורב לטעמיה
*veRav leta'ameih*. רב *Rav* goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רב *de'amar
Rav*, because רב *Rav* says: אין מבוי mavoi ניתר בלחי וקורה *ein
mavoi nittar belechi vekorah*. You can only carry in a מבוי mavoi
*mavoi* if you make a לחי *lechi* and a קורה *korah*, meaning
like, again, this like vertical or horizontal beam. That only works to
allow you to carry in a מבוי mavoi. *mavoi* עד שיהו בתים
וחצרות פתוחים לתוכו *ad sheyehu battim vachatzeros petuchim letocho*, only if you
have a classic מבוי mavoi, *mavoi*, a classic alleyway, that has houses
and courtyards open into it. והכא, בתים איכא חצרות ליכא *vehacha, battim
ika chatzeros leka*. And in this case, you have houses, you don't
have courtyards. Meaning what? Your
classic scenario is, like I drew over here,
right?
Here's your alleyway, your מבוי mavoi, *mavoi*. It has these
חצר chatzer. *chatzer*... But what we're saying is is that this idea
that you can use the alleyway, it has to be a classic
alleyway. There has to be multiple חצרות that open into it, and
each חצר chatzer, has to have at least two houses into the
חצר. chatzer Okay, well you have that here. But now what we're
saying is ah, but here, once you did the עירוב eruv by
the חצר, chatzer each חצר chatzer based on this fiction of the
עירוב eruv. becomes like a single domain. So every חצר chatzer, turns
into one house. So basically, if you have the, if you've made
them, it's like they're single domains and this מבוי mavoi doesn't have
חצרות opening into it. It only has effectively houses opening into it
and not חצרות. Now that's obviously a little strange because then how
would you ever be allowed to carry in the alleyway? Because so
obviously the point is, okay, if you do everything the way you're
supposed to do, if you then you don't need that idea because
conceptually it all everything becomes one domain. But to the degree that
you did not do a שיתוף shituf. in the מבוי, mavoi you
did not join together in the מבוי, mavoi then we're only it's
a little still a little ironic, but we're only going to allow
you to carry in it if it's like a classic מבוי. mavoi?
If it has a חצר chatzer, open into it, and here you've
turned the חצרות into houses. Again, I really can't explain it any
better. Just know in a few lines we're going to reject it,
okay?
But that's at least what the גמרא Gemara, is saying here. So
כאילו עירבו, ke'ilu eirvu, anyway he doesn't even understand that. Even if
I accept that, that now the חצרות have turned effectively into houses
and that's why it doesn't work. כאילו עירבו נמי, ke'ilu eirvu nami,
so even if they didn't do an עירוב, eruv, לחזינהו להני בתי
כמאן דסתמי דמו. lechezeinhu lehani batei keman desatmi damu. So let's look
at the houses as if they're sealed off, וחצרות איכא בתי ליכא,
vechatzerot ika batei leika, and you have the courtyards, you don't have
the houses. Because if you didn't make an עירוב eruv, in each
individual חצר, chatzer. you cannot carry from the house into the חצר,
chatzer right? You didn't make an עירוב. eruv So then these houses
have no access into the מבוי. mavoi They even have no access
into the חצר. chatzer, So these houses become irrelevant. They're like cut
off because you made no שיתוף. shituf, So then the only things
that's relevant for the מבוי mavoi, is the חצר chatzer. and not
the houses. So you're saying if you made an if you made
an עירוב, eruv. it's all the חצרות become like a house. But
if you didn't make an עירוב, eruv you've cut off all the
houses. So why should that be okay? You still don't have the
classic configuration of houses and courtyards. So the גמרא Gemara says, אפשר,
efshar, no, there I have an answer. אפשר דמבטלי להו רשותא דכולהו
לגבי חד, efshar demavtlei lehu reshuta dechulehu legabi chad, even if you
didn't make an עירוב eruv in the חצר, chatzer there's a way
in which you can carry without making an עירוב. eruv Everybody could
nullify their private domain like for the sake of one of the
people. So even without having done the עירוב eruv ahead of time,
they can waive their sort of private ownership for, you know again,
it's like a fiction, but they can waive it for one person
and allow carrying in the courtyard. That's called ביטול רשות. bitul reshut.
So even without having done an having done an, you can effectively
get to that end result. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but
if you're if you're now saying that that you can affect it
that everybody has that it's all under one person's control, you're back
to the first problem. סוף סוף, sof sof, says the גמרא, Gemara
in the end analysis, בית איכא בתים ליכא, bayit ika batim leika,
what you'll wind up doing is having effectively one house and not
multiple houses. Okay, because one person has
the only
house is effectively the one who has reownership. גמרא Gemara says, no,
אפשר, efshar, it's possible דמצפר ועד פלגא דיומא לגבי חד, demitzafra ve'ad
palga deyoma legabi chad,
maybe for the first half of the day you waive the control
to one
person, ומיפלגא דיומא ולפניא לגבי חד, umipalga deyoma ulefanya legabi chad, you
waive it to the other person. So what the גמרא Gemara. is
saying is, again, this is quite ironic, but it's saying is that
if you do a שיתוף, shituf, then you turn this into one
big domain, and then it's like a house. It's not a חצר.
chatzer. If you don't do a שיתוף, shituf, so the חצר chatzer
retains its identity, and then the houses get access based on this
other fiction of being מבטל mevatel their רשות. reshut. So because you
didn't do a שיתוף, shituf you didn't transform the חצר. chatzer. Because
they waive their rights to one person, that also gives them access,
and now it's like the houses and the חצר chatzer, have access.
What about the idea that you need two houses? So you take
turns. Half of the day one person has rights, the other day
the other person has rights. So the גמרא Gemara says, nevertheless,
סוף סוף, sof sof, בעידנא דאיתא להאי ליתא להאי, be'idna de'ita lehai
leita lehai, when one person has is the one that has is
the owner, the other person is not. So you still don't have
the classic configuration of a courtyard with two houses. All right, so
that was all very confusing, but and now the גמרא Gemara finally
like rejects that. But that was an attempt to say why can't
you carry in here? Because you don't have the classic configuration of
a courtyard with houses. Although you do physically, somehow with when you
have the when you have
the the עירוב חצרות, eruv chatzerot, it somehow reconfigures it and it
doesn't have the classic configuration, which makes you wonder why you ever
have the classic configuration. But anyway, that's the גמרא. Gemara assertion, and
the גמרא's Gemara, not happy now because it says, okay, it doesn't
matter then, anyway you do it you don't have this classic houses
and courtyards. אלא אמר רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, so fine,
forget that whole approach. Here's what רב אשי Rav Ashi says: מי
גרם לחצרות שיאסרו
בתים וליכא. Mi garam lachatzeros she'ye'asru batim v'leka. What makes the courtyards
forbidden? It's the houses, and that's not around. What does that mean?
It means the following.
It means
a much easier explanation.
You want to carry in this מבוי mavoi. with something that was
left in the מבוי. mavoi Okay, so it's true, all of these
courtyards have not made a שיתוף shituf with the מבוי, mavoi. so
you can't carry from the courtyard into the מבוי, mavoi. but you
only want to carry within the מבוי mavoi. itself. Okay, but there's
a problem because the מבוי mavoi is open to the חצר. chatzer,
Does the presence of the חצר, chatzer is that seen of as
a separate domain that opens up into the מבוי mavoi and problematizes
the מבוי? mavoi, Or are these courtyards considered to be an extension
of the מבוי mavoi and it's all effectively one domain? So it
says, look, here's the issue. If you can carry from the houses
into the חצר, chatzer okay, then this makes the חצר chatzer, a
very different type of a domain than the מבוי, mavoi. because the
חצר chatzer has all this stuff going in and out from these
houses, right, so it's not just about this yard, it's about, you
know, it has access to the houses and vice versa, so that
makes it a different domain than the מבוי. mavoi And the fact
that it's open into the מבוי mavoi means that now that problematizes
the מבוי. mavoi It's not all just one big like open space.
It's got parts of it that aren't that aren't connected. And you
certainly can't, for example, carry from the houses into the מבוי. mavoi
So if you made an עירוב in the חצר, chatzer. now you
have a problem because now the חצר chatzer? is used by the
houses and is a separate domain than the מבוי. mavoi And therefore
the מבוי mavoi being open to those separate domains, you can't even
carry in the מבוי mavoi itself. If you have not made, starting
to get very anyway, if you have not made it, then the
houses are irrelevant to the חצר. chatzer, Then all you have is
just an open yard open into the מבוי, mavoi and it doesn't
have the use of the houses, and therefore it's considered one type
of a domain with the מבוי mavoi and you can carry in
the מבוי. Yes, Charlie.
So the מבוי must be at a biblical level a רשות היחיד?
reshus hayachid, Yes, all of these are biblical רשות reshus, היחיד, all
of these are purely rabbinic problems. Okay, so let's just read that
again. אלא אמר רב אשי מי גרם לחצרות שיאסרו
בתים וליכא.
Ella amar Rav Ashi mi garam lachatzeros she'ye'asru
batim v'leka. Meaning, what makes the, when there is no שיתוף shituf
עירוב of חצרות, what normally would make the חצרות a problem on
the מבוי to carry from the מבוי into the חצר? chatzer, It's
the presence of the houses that the houses are have use of
it and that's something that don't have access to the מבוי and
makes it a very different type of a domain. וליכא, V'leka, if
you have not made a שיתוף in the, an עירוב in the
חצר, chatzer the houses are like not relevant, so it's all just
open yards, it's all one domain and since you can now carry
from the מבוי into the חצר, you can also carry from the
מבוי within itself. It's not open to a problematic space. That's one
answer. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. Okay, so that's the end of it.
So that was a little complicated digression, it's also a little bit
of an appetizer for all of מסכת עירובין. Masechet Eruvin. Okay, so
get ready, it's about a month away. Anyway, back to what we
our main focus which was all of that was about because they
talked about bringing a מילה milah knife from one חצר to the
next or from the end of one מבוי to the next and
now we have to talk about sometimes according to one opinion sometimes
a מבוי is problematic even within the מבוי if the houses have
access to the courtyards that surround it. Now back to רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer position about doing מכשירי מילה milah on שבת. Shabbos, Let's
take a look. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן לא
לכל אמר רבי אליעזר מכשירי מצוה דוחין את השבת. Amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan lo l'chol amar Rabbi Eliezer machshirei mitzvah
dochin es haShabbos. Not for all purposes did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
say that the things that could the preparatory acts for for a
מצוה mitzvah can be done on שבת, Shabbos, meaning maybe we'll abstract
it, maybe it's not just limited to ברית מילה. bris milah, Maybe
he says that any מצוה mitzvah that can be done on שבת,
Shabbos, all of its preparations can be done on שבת, Shabbos, making
it even more radical. Now that seems extreme, like probably wouldn't have
occurred to anybody here to say that. I mean מילה mila we
know overrides שבת, Shabbos. so therefore maybe some things come with it,
not necessarily other things. But the reason the גמרא Gemara is going
to say it as we're going to see there's going to be
ברייתות beraisos that extend רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to many many more
מצוות. mitzvos. So the גמרא Gemara is saying, okay, it might extend
to other מצוות mitzvos but not to everything. How do you know
that? שהרי
שתי הלחם חובת היום הן. Sheharei shtei halechem chovas hayom hen. One
of the things we'll see it extend to will be the שתי
הלחם, shtei halechem, the two loaves of bread that are brought
on שבועות. Shavuos. Now those are things that are brought on the
day itself and they override the יום טוב Yom Tov or even
if it falls out on שבת, Shabbos, they can be done on
שבת. Shabbos. ולא למדן רבי אליעזר אלא מגזרה שוה. V'lo lamdan Rabbi
Eliezer ela migzeirah shavah. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, said not only
can you bring the שתי הלחם shtei halechem even if it falls
out on a שבת, Shabbos? you can even do the מכשירים, machshirim,
even cut it and harvest the wheat and bake it, everything you
can do to bring it on the right day. Okay, so that's
consistent with his position that you can do the מכשירים, machshirim, the
preparatory stages even on שבת. Shabbos. However, says the גמרא, Gemara he
didn't just learn it. by just a regular abstracting. He says, I
know this by מילה mila. apply it across the board. He had
to learn it from a specific דרשה. drasha. He had to learn
it from a גזירה שוה. gezera shava. So he has to learn
it from גזירה שוה gezera shava it means it's not a universal
rule. It means I have a local rule here, I can apply
it to a few cases that I have a particular way of
making a דרשה drasha to apply it to, but I can't just
assume I apply it across the board. So גמרא Gemara is saying
although he does do it in other cases, it's because he has
a specific לימוד limud and he does not do it universally. And
here he only did it because of גזירה שוה. gezera shava. Let's
take a look.
דתניא, Ditanyu, תני בברייתא, tani b'braisa, רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer:
מניין למכשירין של שתי הלחם שדוחה את השבת? minayin l'machshirin shel shtei
halechem she'dochen es haShabbos? How do I know that the preparatory acts
of making the loaves of bread for שבועות Shavuos can override שבת?
Shabbos, נאמר הובאה בעומר ne'emar hava'ah b'omer because it says by עומר,
omer, והבאתם את עומר, v'havaysam es omer, you should bring the עומר.
omer. ונאמר הובאה בשתי הלחם v'ne'emar hava'ah b'she'elechem and it says by
these two loaves of bread that you should bring the two loaves
of
bread, תביאו לחם תנופה. taviu lechem tenufa. Okay, so מה הובאה האמורה
בעומר מכשירין דוחה את השבת, mah hava'ah ha'amura b'omer machshirin dochen es
haShabbos, the same way the preparatory stages of the עומר omer override
שבת. Shabbos. And how do you know that? Because it's a separate
דרשה drasha actually. Because it says by actually last week's parsha, right?
It says בחריש ובקציר תשבות, becharish uvaktzir tishbos, in the harvesting and
in the plowing and the harvesting you shall rest. And one of
the דרשות drashos is is that this is talking about the same
way plowing is a רשות, reshus there's never a מצוה mitzvah to
plow on שבת, Shabbos then therefore the only resting you have to
do from harvesting is resting that's a רשות reshus, as opposed to
resting that I mean harvesting that's a רשות, excuse me, as opposed
to harvesting that's a מצוה, mitzvah, קציר katzir that is a מצוה,
mitzvah, that you don't stop on שבת. Shabbos. What type of a
קציר katzir is a מצוה? mitzvah? So it's קציר העומר. katzir ha'omer.
It says וקצרתם, uktzartem, right? There's a specific מצוה mitzvah to harvest.
So that says the only harvesting you don't do on שבת Shabbos
is harvesting that is like plowing, that is optional. But harvesting that's
a מצוה, mitzvah, that you do on שבת. Shabbos. So we know
that on the עומר, omer, even the cutting of the wheat for
the עומר omer can be done on שבת Shabbos, when the עומר
omer when the day falls out on שבת. Shabbos Okay, not like
a week in advance, but when the day falls out on שבת,
Shabbos. you can do it. So the same way that by the
עומר, omer, מה הובאה האמורה בעומר מכשירין דוחה את השבת, mah hava'ah
ha'amura b'omer machshirin dochin es haShabbos, the same way by the עומר
omer you can harvest the wheat on שבת Shabbos. if that's the
day of the bringing of the עומר, omer, אף הובאה האמורה בשתי
הלחם מכשירין דוחה את השבת, af hava'ah ha'amura b'shtei halechem machshirin dochin
es haShabbos, even by the two loaves of bread on שבועות, Shavuos,
okay, you can do the harvesting on שבת. Shabbos. So you see
he learned it from a גזירה שוה. gezera shava. He did not
just learn a general principle that from עומר omer or from מילה.
milah No, he needed a specific גזירה שוה gezera shava to apply
עומר omer to the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. Now the גמרא Gemara
says מופני. mufni. By the way, this גזירה שוה gezera shava is
open-ended. Meaning מופני mufni means, right, we connect two words, but if
the words are used for their own purpose like in the local
context of the פסוק, pasuk, then you may not be able to
make a גזירה שוה gezera shava because the words have to do
their own function. It's only when the words are seen as extra,
מופני, mufni, like they're open, that then you can make a גזירה
שוה. gezera shava. So the גמרא Gemara is saying מופני, mufni, these
words of הובאה hava'ah are open, are not used. דאי לא מופני,
de'i lo mufni, if they weren't used, איכא למיפרך, ika l'mifrach, because
maybe there's a general idea that maybe you might be able to
make a גזירה שוה gezera shava if the words aren't extra, but
then it can be challenged. The only type of a גזירה שוה
gezera shava that's ironclad that cannot be challenged is if the words
that you are linking together are considered to be extra. Then it's
only there to serve as a גזירה שוה, gezera shava, no questions
asked. But if the words aren't extra, then you can challenge it
logically. So the גמרא Gemara is saying this has to be that
the words are extra because if not, this גזירה שוה gezera shava
could be challenged. How could it be challenged? מה לעומר שכן אם
מצא קצור קוצר. mah l'omer shekein im matza katzur kotzer. By עומר
omer there's a specific מצוה mitzvah to harvest the grain. If it
happened to be that came along the second day of פסח, Pesach,
you have grain that had already been harvested not for the purpose
of the עומר, omer, you wouldn't be able to use it. You'd
have to specifically harvest the grain for the purpose of the עומר.
omer. So there's a מצוה mitzvah to do the act of cutting.
It's not just getting the grain. And that's why the cutting overrides
שבת. Shabbos, תאמר בשתי הלחם שאם מצא קצור אינו קוצר. tomar b'shtei
halechem she'im matza katzur eino kotzer.
But by the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, right, and by the way,
right, think about it. By the עומר omer this is supposed to
be the first harvesting. By the time שבועות Shavuos rolls around, people
have been harvesting grain for fifty days, for seven weeks. So by
the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, even if grain was there's no idea
of doing an act of cutting like there's a מצוה mitzvah to
harvest. So and even if you had grain that was already cut,
you could use it. So once that's true, there's no reason to
think that that would override שבת. Shabbos. By עומר omer I understand
why it overrides שבת, Shabbos there's a מצוה mitzvah to cut it.
Not by the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. So therefore if you didn't
have the גזירה שוה gezera shava that was ironclad, you would not
be able to apply this principle to the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem.
So now the גמרא Gemara says לאי, la'ee, is this really true?
פנויי מופנה, panuyei mufneh, it's really open? מכדי, michdi, let's take a
look.
כתיב והבאתם עומר ראשית קצירכם אל הכהן. ksiv v'havaysam omer reishis katzirchem
el hakohein. So here's how it would be open. It says you
should bring the עמר, omer, the first of your harvesting to the
כהן. kohen. ביום הביאכם, B'yom havichem, the day that you bring, למה
לי? lama li? That's extra, right? It's clear that it's in the
context of the day that you're bringing, ביום הביאכם, B'yom havichem, את
עמר התנופה. et omer hatnufah. So that's seen as extra words. שמע
מינה לאתנויי, Shma mina le-atnu'ei, to make the whole פסוק pasuk open
for גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah. Although it's interesting, the גזירה שוה gezerah
shavah is done on the word והבאתם, vahavatem, bringing, but the ביום
הביאכם B'yom havichem is somehow since some of the words are extra,
that allows for this גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah. So the גמרא Gemara
says, I'm still not happy. ואכתי מופנה מצד אחד הוא. Ve-aketi mufne
mitzad echad hu. So one of the ends of the גזירה שוה
gezerah shavah is extra, has extra words, the עמר omer end. ושמעינן
ליה לרבי אליעזר, Ve-shamin leh le-Rabbi Eliezer, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
is of the position, this is all רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer. דאמר
מופנה מצד אחד למידין ומשיבין. de-amar mufne mitzad echad lamedin u-meshivin. Even
if it's unused at one end, it's not ironclad. It's only ironclad
if both parts of the גזירה שוה gezerah shavah are extra. But
if only one part is extra, you can make a גזירה שוה,
gezerah shavah, למידין, lamedin, but it's also open to challenge, משיבין. meshivin.
Okay, so therefore he says that in another context. So here, if
we want to make a גזירה שוה, gezerah shavah, since this whole
thing can obviously be logically challenged, we need both ends to be
open. So the גמרא Gemara says fine. תביאו ריבויה הוא. Tavi'u ribuyu
hu. By the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem as well, it says תביאו
לחם תנופה, tavi'u lechem tnufah, you should bring, and that word תביאו
tavi'u is seen as extra or as more inclusive. It could have
said תביא tavi or could have maybe not said the word at
all. So somehow we have a little extras in both places that
allow the גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah. Alright, but the upshot being that
number one, which is an important point number one, is where does
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, learn this principle that מכשירין machshirim of מילה
milah are דוחה שבת? docheh Shabbos? First of all, where do we
even learn that מילה milah. is דוחה שבת? docheh Shabbos? Well we'll
get to that a little bit later, maybe tomorrow. But where do
you learn that מכשירין? machshirim? So maybe here at least here's a
good source, not about ברית מילה, bris milah? but here's a good
source by the עמר. omer. The עמר omer based on the פסוק
passuk as we know that there's a מצוה mitzvah to be קוצר,
kotzer, and בחריש ובקציר be-charish u-va-katzir we know that the cutting of
the עמר omer is דוחה שבת docheh Shabbos even though it's preparatory.
So maybe that serves as the general principle for all other מצוות
mitzvos that are done on שבת. Shabbat? So the גמרא Gemara says
look, it might be that we learn it from there, we'll see
in a minute where we learn other things, but that does not
mean that it becomes a universal principle and it can be applied
in all cases. Every case we apply it to, we need a
specific לימוד limud according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer The same way
he needed a גזירה שוה gezerah shavah to apply it to שתי
הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, and we'll see later he needs other פסוקים pesukim
to learn everything he applies it to. So it might be he
applies it to many, many cases but he doesn't apply it everywhere.
Every case needs a special לימוד. limud. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara is going to say okay, so what cases is he going
to exclude?
So לאתויי מאי, le-atuyei mai, which cases will he not apply it
to? אילימא לאתויי לולב, Ileima le-atuyei lulav, maybe you'll say לולב. lulav.
Now why should you exclude לולב? lulav? Why would not just לולב
lulav in itself? But what makes לולב lulav of a different type
of a מצוה mitzvah that's done on שבת Shabbat. than something like
the עמר, omer, the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem or the ברית מילה?
bris milah
Can you think about within the context of overriding שבת?
Shabbat, Well you don't take the לולב lulav on שבת.
Shabbat, Well we rabbinically don't take it, but biblically you would. But
when you take the לולב lulav on שבת, Shabbat, you're not violating
anything. To do a ברית מילה bris milah on שבת, Shabbat, to
do the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem on שבת, Shabbat to do the
עמר omer on שבת, Shabbos. all of those you're doing מלאכה. melachah.
So if the תורה Torah allows a מלאכה melachah to be done
in the performance of the מצוה, mitzvah, argues רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer.
it would allow a מלאכה melachah to be done in the preparatory
stages. But maybe by לולב lulav where the תורה Torah isn't allowing
anything, it's just, hey, take a לולב, lulav, big deal, so where
would I even begin to think that the תורה Torah would give
you license to violate שבת Shabbos to take the לולב? lulav? So
it makes a lot of sense to say he would not say
it on לולב. lulav. But guess what? He does say it by
לולב. lulav. So let's take a look. I built it up so
much, but it's really a shocker that he says it by לולב.
lulav. והא תניא, Ve-ha tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, baraita, לולב
וכל מכשיריו דוחן את השבת דברי רבי אליעזר, lulav ve-chol machshirav dochan
es ha-Shabbos divrei Rabbi Eliezer, that all of the preparations of לולב
lulav override שבת. Shabbos, So that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says.
One wonders, according to him, so probably even rabbinically, why would he
make, would he allow you to take it since he could biblically
violate שבת Shabbos. for it? So if you had to climb up
on a palm tree and cut down a לולב lulav and cut
down an אתרוג, esrog, you'd be allowed to do it according to
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer So even though the מצוה mitzvah itself doesn't
necessarily necessitate violating שבת, Shabbos. since it has to be done today,
anything that's needed to be done in order to have it, in
order to get it done, can be done on שבת. Shabbos. Okay,
so ואלא לאתויי סוכה. ve-ela le-atuyei sukkah. So maybe to, maybe to
exclude סוכה. sukkah. Now once we're including לולב, lulav, you know, סוכה
sukkah isn't any different, but it's the same issue, that the basic
sitting in a סוכה sukkah doesn't require violating שבת. Shabbos, והא תניא,
Ve-ha tanya, but we taught in a ברייתא, baraita, סוכה וכל מכשיריה
דוחן את השבת דברי רבי אליעזר. sukkah ve-chol machshireha dochan es ha-Shabbos
divrei Rabbi Eliezer. No, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, tells you you could
build your סוכה sukkah on שבת. Shabbos. So ואלא לאתויי
מצה. ve-ela le-atuyei matzah. So how about מצה? matzah? Okay, again, doesn't
require any violation. Maybe you can't violate to get it done. והא
תניא, Ve-ha tanya, מצה וכל מכשיריה דוחן את השבת דברי רבי אליעזר.
matzah ve-chol machshireha dochan es ha-Shabbos divrei Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer, says מצה matzah and anything, anything, you can bake your מצות
matzos on שבת, Shabbos not only on יום טוב, Yom Tov, on
שבת. Shabbos Alright, so pretty radical, huh? ואלא לאתויי שופר. ve-ela le-atuyei
shofar. Okay, so you see where this is going. והא תניא. ve-ha
tanya. והתניא V'hatanya תניא ברייתא tanya braisa שופר וכל מכשיריו דוחה את
השבת. shofar v'chol machshirav doche es ha-Shabbos. Mean you could go ahead
and you could cut the שופר shofar off the horn of the
animal
and go ahead and make your שופר shofar on שבת Shabbos. and
carry it in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi
Eliezer. So anyway so now we see that רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer
on the one hand we start by saying he doesn't say it
in all cases. But now we're bringing evidence that he says it
in many cases we would never have expected. He says it in
cases where even the act of the מצוה mitzvah itself doesn't require
violation, he lets you violate in order to prepare the, to get
the מצוה mitzvah object, in order to, in order to make it
possible. Does רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer
does he say this about anything or just these specific things and
if so why?
Well we're going to, that's what we're going to try to see.
So first the גמרא Gemara tries to say, so you said he
doesn't say it everywhere, תני tani something he doesn't say it by,
so we'll see where why he gets, well this is all the
rest of today's דף. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא,
where are we, no, דוחה את השבת, doche es ha-Shabbos, so, דברי
רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. אמר רב
אדא בר אהבה: Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava: למעוטי ציצית לטליתו ומזוזה
לפתחו. l'im'utei tzitzis l'taliso u'mezuzah l'pischu. Here's the thing you can't do.
You can't make ציצית tzitzis on your garment on שבת Shabbos, or
put up a מזוזה mezuzah on שבת. Shabbos, תניא נמי הכי: Tanya
nami hachi: וכולן שוין, v'chulan shavin, but they agree, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and וחכמים, v'Chachamim, שאם ציץ טליתו she'im tzitz taliso if he
put ציצית tzitzis on his garment ועשה מזוזה לפתחו v'asah mezuzah l'pischu
you put a מזוזה mezuzah up on your doorpost בשבת, be-Shabbos, שהוא
חייב. shehu chayav. So finally with that at least רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer? would say you're חייב. chayav. Now, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why
is that different? So it seems the difference is obvious, which is
what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: לפי
שאין קבוע להם זמן. lefi she-ein kavua lahem zman. Because it's not
a fixed time. It's not like the תורה Torah says you have
to do it today. So if you have to do it today,
you know the same way, for example, you bring a קרבן פסח
korban Pesach on שבת, Shabbos. you bring a תמיד tamid on שבת,
Shabbos. one of the reasons is it says במועדו, b'moado, in its
time. So maybe since today is the day I have to take
לולב lulav and שופר, shofar, everything gets overridden for me to be
able to take it today. But something like ציצית tzitzis and מזוזה,
mezuzah, I don't have to do it today, I'll do it tomorrow.
So therefore it doesn't override שבת. Shabbos, So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, said to him אביי: אדרבה, aderaba,
the opposite makes sense. מכדי אין קבוע להם זמן, michdi ein kavua
lahem zman, since there's no fixed time, כל שעתא ושעתא זמניה הוא,
kol sha'ata v'sha'ata zimneih hu,
every time is its obligation. Which is the way תוספות Tosafos explains
it, he says if I put up a מזוזה mezuzah tomorrow and
not today, yes I'm doing the מצוה mitzvah tomorrow but I did
not do the מצוה mitzvah today. If I put ציצית tzitzis on
my garment tomorrow, fine, from tomorrow on I'll have done the מצוה,
mitzvah, but I wouldn't have done today's מצוה mitzvah of ציצית. tzitzis.
So therefore, if you don't do it today you're going to blow
today's מצוה. mitzvah. So why should that weaken it? The same way
if I don't do לולב lulav today I'll have blown today's taking
of the לולב. lulav. So if I don't do ציצית tzitzis today
I'll have blown today's wearing of ציצית. tzitzis. So why just because
לולב lulav is less frequent does it create a greater demand, if
the reality is that each day is a separate מצוה mitzvah and
if I don't do it I lose today's מצוה? mitzvah? אלא אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק,
Ella
amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, ואיתימא, v'isayma, and some say רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע, Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, הואיל ובידו להפקירן, ho'il u'veyado
l'hafkiro, a very sense, a very secondary reason, because you don't have
to, you're not strictly obligated to make, to do ציצית tzitzis or
מזוזה mezuzah today, why? Because you could let's say renounce ownership of
your house, renounce ownership of your clothes, and therefore you don't have
to do it, it's not so much a personal obligation like לולב,
lulav, שופר, shofar, סוכה sukkah where basically the point is I don't
care who you are or where you are, you've got to do
this today. Here it's because of the things that you own. So
because it happens to relate to the things that you own, therefore
it is not as much of a personal absolute demand and therefore
does not have the weight to override שבת. Shabbos, So very secondary,
I actually like the first answer better I gotta tell you, somehow
the fact that it's just today is somehow creates I think more
of a focus on it, more of a focused demand than if
it's multiple days, even if every day is its own מצוה. mitzvah.
But anyway, the bottom line is only a few trivial things רבי
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer, says don't override שבת, Shabbos but other מצוות, mitzvos,
even if the performance of the מצוה mitzvah does not require overriding
שבת, Shabbos? you would be allowed to violate שבת Shabbos in order
to get it done. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to
discuss where he learns that from the פסוקים pesukim since we're saying
it's not a general rule for him. Yes?
I can just declare property הפקר hefker on שבת?
Shabbos Well yeah, I mean that's an interesting question about does it
fall under the problem of קניין kinyan on שבת Shabbos. and so
on. But for the purposes here even if רבנן rabbanan you can't,
מדאורייתא mid'oraisa you can, and it's really a larger point about the
fact that it's not so much about fully about you absolutely being
demanded, being obligated, it's about only under certain circumstances. So it's not
the same sense of an absolute obligation as by the others. Okay,
so let's take a look.
Because by סוכה sukkah also you could say that on other days
of סוכות Sukkos I don't have to eat, so I don't have
to eat in a סוכה. sukkah. Anyway, אמר מר. amar mar.
So now we're going to look at where we learn it from
the פסוקים pesukim because now we're arguing that he has to learn
this all from פסוקים. pesukim. לולב וכל מכשיריו דוחה את השבת דברי
רבי אליעזר. lulav v'chol machshirav doche es ha-Shabbos divrei Rabbi Eliezer. מנא
ליה לרבי אליעזר הא? mina lei l'Rabbi Eliezer ha? Where does he
learn this from? אי מהני שתי הלחם? ei me-hanei shtei ha-lechem? If
you want to say from שתי הלחם? shtei ha-lechem? שכן צורך גבוה.
she-ken tzorech gavoha. That's different, that's given to God. So it's not
the same as just a normal מצוה, mitzvah, that's something that's actually
presented in the בית המקדש. Beis ha-Mikdash. Of course, the stronger distinction
is those are things that they themselves override שבת Shabbos. as opposed
to לולב lulav which it itself normally does not override שבת. Shabbos,
But anyway, that would, either way, you can't learn from there and
we said you need a separate פסוק pasuk for each thing. אלא
אמר קרא ביום. ella amar kra bayom. You should do on the
day, you know, ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון. ulekachtem lachem bayom harishon.
You should take on the first day. So ביום, bayom, אפילו בשבת.
afilu b'shabbos. On the day regardless, sort of like, it has to
be done today, even on שבת. Shabbos. ולמאי אוקמה? ulemai okma? What
for what reason is it saying day? אילימא לטלטול? eileima letiltul? If
it's just for the normal taking of the מצוה, mitzvah, איצטריך למישרי
טלטול? itztarech lemishrei tiltul? You don't need a פסוק passuk to allow
me to take a לולב, lulav, right? Whatever לולב lulav is, מוקצה,
muktzeh, whatever the concerns of מוקצה muktzeh is, it's only רבנן. rabanan.
So if the פסוק passuk is telling you do it on שבת,
Shabbos it's not just telling you do the act, that you wouldn't
need a פסוק passuk for that.
אלא למכשיריו, ela lemachshirav, to tell you even the preparatory things can
be done on שבת. Shabbos, רבנן, rabanan, what do the Rabbis say
who argue on רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer הוא מיבעי ליה ביום ולא
בלילה. hu mibayei lei bayom velo balailah. You only take the לולב
lulav in the day, not at night. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer ביום
ולא בלילה מנא ליה? bayom velo balailah mana lei? Where does he
know the idea of daytime and not nighttime? נפקא ליה מ ושמחתם
לפני ה' אלקיכם שבעת ימים, nafka lei mi usmachtem lifnei Hashem Elokeichem
shivas yamim, you rejoice before God seven days, the end of the
פסוק passuk of taking the לולב. lulav. ימים ולא לילות, yamim velo
leilos, only days is the מצוה mitzvah of לולב. lulav. ורבנן, v'rabanan,
איצטריך. itztarech. The Rabbis say you need that פסוק. passuk. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, salka da'atach amina, נגמר שבעת ימים מסוכה, nigmar shivas yamim misukkah,
I might have said that since there's a seven days by the
לולב lulav here, at least in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, I'll
learn out the seven days from סוכה. sukkah. מה להלן ימים אפילו
לילות, ma hahlan yamim afilu leilos, the same way there by סוכה
sukkah it applies day and night, אף כאן ימים אפילו לילות, af
kan yamim afilu leilos, here too maybe it applies at night, קא
משמע לן, ka mashma lan, okay. So therefore that has to say
that even the seven day aspect of לולב, lulav, which is in
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, is only daytime not nighttime. Anyway, bottom
line is that he adds the extra word ביום bayom to tell
me that it's done today regardless, even if it requires violation. So
נכתוב רחמנא בלולב ונייתי הנך וניגמר מיניה. nichtav rachmana b'lulav v'neisi hanach
v'nigmar mineih.
So just write it by לולב. lulav. לולב lulav is a normal
מצוה, mitzvah, it's not like a קרבן korban type of a thing,
and if by לולב lulav overrides, certainly the קרבנות korbanos should, and
then we'll learn the קרבנות korbanos from it. No, משום דאיכא למפרך,
mishum d'ika l'mifrach, because it can be challenged. מה לולב שכן טעון
ארבעה מינים, ma lulav shekein taun arba minim, לולב lulav may be
special that you have four separate components of it. And therefore because
it has four separate components, maybe it has particular weight to be
done on שבת Shabbat. more than קרבנות. korbanos. It's pretty funny, right?
Normally of course we assume that קרבנות korbanos have greater weight and
the קרבן korban itself is done on שבת, Shabbat, but maybe the
idea that it has ארבעה מינים arba minim gives it some special
weight. I would say by the way it's an interesting
framing, שכן טעון ארבעה מינים, shekein taun arba minim, it sort of
necessitates ארבעה מינים. arba minim. Normally, you know,
הלכתית halachically you would think that each of the ארבעה מינים arba
minim are of equal weight, right? The תורה Torah says take four
things. Then you wouldn't say טעון ארבעה מינים, taun arba minim, you'd
say שכן יש בו ארבעה מינים shekein yesh bo arba minim or
something like that. טעון taun makes it sound like the basic מצוה
mitzvah is the לולב lulav and the other things are like accompaniment
to the לולב, lulav, which to some degree is how we make
the ברכה bracha and how we think about it, right? We say
על נטילת לולב, al netilas lulav, we don't say על נטילת ארבעה
מינים. al netilas arba minim. So it seems that that's also conceptually
how the גמרא Gemara here is framing it. Yes, Rivka, you have
a question?
I'm just uncomfortable with that צורך גבוה tzorech gavoah again. Here it
seems so clear they're saying God needs that bread.
Yeah, again, I understand, I was actually thinking about that as I
was reading it.
God is hungry for that bread, we gotta give the bread.
I understand, you know, all I can say is that it's sort
of a continuation, first of all גבוה gavoah here I guess could
mean also like the temple, it's needs of the temple, but what
can I say, it's just continuing the metaphor that's already in the
תורה, Torah, you know, the imagery that's in the תורה, Torah, it's
a way of distinguishing.
But it is such a metaphor because they're separating out things that
don't get consumed.
I know, but the תורה Torah itself, right, ריח ניחוח, reiach nichoach,
לחם אשה לה'. lechem isheh la'Hashem. I mean, this is a lot
more abstract than it is in the תורה. Torah. So I understand
that, I mean, but yeah, that
there is that way of thinking about it. I know that God
needs the קרבן korban more than he needs, I understand.
One interesting question is how we got from this kind of language
to like רש"י's Rashi language where it clearly says that God is
pleased not so much with the odor but the fact that we
fulfill the commandment.
Right, right,
and that's I mean it's very much in Rabbinic literature, the moving
away from that much more, you know, very, right, those heavy anthropomorphisms
and so on. צורך גבוה tzorech gavoah is pretty abstract, you know,
but you are right that it's, I
don't know, it's not so abstract.
I don't know, yeah, גבוה gavoah is גבוה, gavoah, God
needs this, I
understand, I understand, yeah, I get it. Alright, so let's see now
the, so that's לולב. lulav. Now, סוכה דקא מכשיריה דחו את השבת,
sukkah d'ka machshireha dachu es haShabbos, דברי רבי אליעזר, divrei Rebbi Eliezer,
מנא ליה לרבי אליעזר, mana lei le'Rebbi Eliezer, what about סוכה? sukkah?
If you need a separate פסוק passuk for everything, where does he
learn סוכה sukkah from? אימא משתי הלחם, eima mishtei halechem, it's from
the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, שכן צורך גבוה, shekein tzorech gavoah, again
that phrase, that's something for the temple. הוי אומר, hevei omer, if
it's לולב, lulav, so maybe that has special weight. If it's לולב,
lulav, שכן טעון ארבעה מינים, shekein taun arba minim, that has the
four מינים, minim, that gives it special weight. אלא גמר משבעת ימים
מלולב, ela gmar mishivas yamim milulav, a גזרה שוה, gezeirah shavah, because
it says by סוכה שבעת ימים sukkah shivas yamim and by לולב
שבעת ימים, lulav shivas yamim, one aspect of לולב, lulav, ושמחתם לפני
ה' אלקיכם. usmachtem lifnei Hashem Elokeichem. מה להלן מכשיריו דוחין את השבת
אף כאן נמי מכשיריו דוחין את השבת. ma hahlan machshirav dochin es
haShabbos af kan nami machshirav dochin es haShabbos. So the same way
by לולב lulav we learned it out, we apply it to סוכה.
sukkah. ונכתוב רחמנא בסוכה ונייתי הנך וניגמר מינה, v'nichtav rachmana b'sukkah v'neisi
hanach v'nigmar minah, why not just write it by סוכה sukkah and
then we'll apply it? Because these other things are weightier because they're
temple based or ארבעה מינים. arba minim. משום דאיכא למפרך, mishum d'ika
l'mifrach, no, סוכה sukkah has an aspect that's... The same way by
לולב Lulav we learned it out, we apply it to סוכה. Sukkah.
ולכתוב רחמנא בסוכה ונייתי הנך ונגמור מינה, V'lichtov Rachmana beSukkah v'neiti hanach
v'nigmor minei, why not just write it by סוכה Sukkah and then
we'll apply it? Because these other things are weightier because they're temple-based
or ארבע מינים. Arba Minim. ומשום דאיכא למיפרך, U'mishum d'ika l'mifrach, no,
סוכה Sukkah has an aspect that's weightier that I could not have
learned it from, applied it from there elsewhere. What? שכן נוהג בלילות
ובימים, Sheken noheg baleilot u'vayamim, סוכה Sukkah applies night and day, all
these other things are only daytime, so maybe that gave it special
weight. So since it has special weight, each thing has to be
learned separately. You cannot take one and apply it
elsewhere. מצה וכל מכשיריה דוחים את השבת דרבי אליעזר, Matzah ve'chol machshireiha
dochin et haShabbat de'Rabbi Eliezer, this is so very fast, stop. So
מנלן לדרבי אליעזר הא, Menalan le'Rabbi Eliezer ha, where does he know
the מצה? Matzah? אי נימא משתי הלחם Ei neima mishtei halechem שכן
צורך גבוה, sheken tzorech gavoah, again you can't learn it from שתי
הלחם, shtei halechem, that's a קרבן. korban. אי מלולב Ei miLulav שכן
טעון ארבעה מינים, sheken ta'un arba'ah minim, לולב Lulav has special weight,
you can't apply it because of the ארבעה מינים. arba'ah minim. אי
מסוכה Ei miSukkah שכן נוהגת בלילות כבימים, sheken noheget baleilot k'vayamim, סוכה
Sukkah special weight it applies at night, so how can
you apply it to מצה? Matzah? Or applies at night and day,
מצה Matzah is only night. אלא גמר חמישה עשר חמישה עשר מחג
הסוכות, Ella gamar chamishah asar chamishah asar mechag haSukkot, another גזירה שוה
gezeirah shavah continuing the chain. By סוכות Sukkot it says on the
fifteenth and מצה Matzah it says on the fifteenth, so מה להלן
מכשירין דוחים את השבת, mah lehalan machshirin dochin et haShabbat, the same
way by סוכה Sukkah we learned it overrides Shabbat and all the
preparatory, אף כאן מכשירין דוחים את השבת af kan machshirin dochin et
haShabbat by מצה Matzah as well. ולכתוב רחמנא במצה ונייתו הנהו וליגמרו
מינה, V'lichtov Rachmana beMatzah v'neitu hanhu v'ligmru mineih, write it by מצה
Matzah and apply it to all these others if all these others
are weightier? No, ומשום דאיכא למיפרך, U'mishum d'ika l'mifrach, no, there's something
that's weightier about מצה. Matzah. שכן מה למצה שכן נוהגת בנשים כבאנשים.
Sheken mah leMatzah sheken noheget benashim k've'anashim. מצה Matzah applies to men
and women, סוכה, Sukkah, לולב Lulav is only to men, the קרבנות,
korbanot, well that's ציבור tzibur I guess, but anyway, but this is
something that even at an individual level applies also to women, that
gives it special weight, so we would not necessarily have assumed that
if it's true here, it's true elsewhere, you know, in other cases
as well. Okay. שופר וכל מכשיריו דוחים את השבת שופר דברי רבי
אליעזר. Shofar ve'chol machshirav dochin et haShabbat Shofar divrei Rabbi Eliezer. מנלן
לדרבי אליעזר הא, Menalan le'Rabbi Eliezer ha, where does he know this?
אי נימא משתי הלחם Ei neima mishtei halechem שכן צורך גבוה, sheken
tzorech gavoah, you can't learn it from שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, that's
a קרבן. korban. אי מלולב Ei miLulav שכן טעון ארבעה מינים, sheken
ta'un arba'ah minim, you can't learn it
from לולב Lulav with the ארבעה מינים. arba'ah minim. אי מסוכה Ei
miSukkah שכן נוהגת בלילות כבימים, sheken noheget baleilot k'vayamim, סוכה Sukkah applies
night and day, שופר Shofar is only day. אי ממצה Ei miMatzah
שכן נוהגת בנשים כבאנשים, sheken noheget benashim k've'anashim, מצה Matzah is men
and women, שופר Shofar biblically is only, is only men. אלא אמר
קרא, Ella amar kra, so how do you know that it applies
by שופר? Shofar? יום תרועה יהיה לכם, Yom teruah yiheyeh lachem, the
day of תרועה. teruah. ביום, Bayom, and the day, this has to
happen today, אפילו בשבת, afilu beShabbat, even on שבת. Shabbat. ולמאי? U'lemai?
Now why would the Torah tell me it overrides Shabbat? אילימא לתקיעה,
Eileima litkiyah, if it's just to tell me you can blow the
שופר. shofar. התנא דבי שמואל, Ha tana d'bei Shmuel, כל מלאכת עבודה
לא תעשו, Kol melechet avodah lo ta'asu, you cannot do work of
labor, or whatever, you know, constructive work. יצא תקיעת שופר ורדיית הפת,
Yatza tkiyat shofar u'rediyat hapat, excluded from מלאכה melacha is blowing שופר
shofar or lowering, taking bread out of the oven, שהיא חכמה shehi
chochmah which is a skill act ואינה מלאכה, ve'einah melacha, but it's
not a מלאכה, melacha, it's not like a creative labor. So it's
only רבנן Rabbanan blowing the שופר shofar on שבת, Shabbat so why
would the Torah have to tell me you can do it? אלא
למכשירין, Ella lemachshirin, if the Torah's telling me blow שופר shofar it
means even if it requires the preparation, requires overriding שבת. Shabbat ורבנן,
Verabbanan, what do the rabbis say that פסוק pasuk is telling me,
ביום? bayom? ההוא מיבעי ליה ביום ולא בלילה, Hahu mibayei lei bayom
velo balailah, to tell me שופר shofar is a daytime מצוה, mitzvah,
not a nighttime מצוה. mitzvah. ורבי אליעזר ביום ולא בלילה מנלן? VeRabbi
Eliezer bayom velo balailah menalan? Where does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer learn
that idea? נפקא
ליה מביום הכפורים תעבירו שופר, Napka lei mi'beYom HaKippurim ta'aviru shofar, from
the שופר shofar of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, where it also says
the day, בכל ארצכם. bechol artzechem. וגמרי אהדדי, Vegamrei ahadadi, and we
learn one from the other. In general, we learned one from the
other to tell me the whole idea of three תרועות teru'ot and
each תרועה teru'ah is preceded by a תקיעה tkiyah before and after.
Okay, so you learn it from the שופר shofar of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur that it's a daytime. ולכתוב רחמנא בשופר, V'lichtov Rachmana beShofar,
back to the other question. Write it by שופר shofar וליתו הנהו
וליגמרו מיניה, v'leitu hanhu v'ligmru mineih, and since שופר shofar is weaker,
if it applies by שופר shofar apply to all these other
מצוות. mitzvot. מתקיעת שופר דראש השנה לא גמרי. Mitkiyat shofar d'Rosh Hashanah
lo gamrei. No, if it had written it by blowing the שופר
shofar on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah you cannot apply it
elsewhere. Why? שכן מכנסת זכרונות של ישראל לאביהם שבשמים. Sheken machneset zichronot
shel Yisrael la'avihem shebashamayim. That's a very powerful statement. תקיעת שופר Tkiyat
shofar is not like other מצוות. mitzvot. It's particularly powerful because it
is used to bring our prayers up to God, or bring our
remembrance up to God. And therefore if the Torah made special allowance
and exceptions to blow the שופר shofar on שבת Shabbat, and violate
שבת Shabbat to do it, maybe specifically because of the importance of
שופר. shofar. I have to say, that's why of all the things
you don't do on שבת, Shabbat. right, the not doing the
שופר shofar on שבת Shabbat. is really very challenging for people, right?
Because it feels, we do it to give that, how could you
have ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah without blowing the שופר? shofar? סוכות Sukkot
without taking the לולב, Lulav, נו, nu, anyway we sit in the
סוכה. Sukkah. So anyway, so therefore I would have thought that that
is a special case that you can even do the
מכשירין machshirin and I couldn't have applied it elsewhere. מתקיעת שופר דיום
הכפורים לא גמרי. Mitkiyat shofar d'Yom HaKippurim lo gamrei. And I couldn't
have just said it by blowing the שופר shofar on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur and then assumed it applies elsewhere. That also is very
weighty. דאמר מר, De'amar mar, because master said, תקעו בבית דין שופר.
tiku be'veit din shofar. What happens when they blew the שופר shofar
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur of the יובל? Yovel? נפטרו עבדים לבתיהם
ושדות חוזרות לבעליהם. Niftaru avadim levateihem vesadot chozrot leva'aleihem. That was what
allowed all the מצוות mitzvot of the יובל Yovel to begin, that
the slaves went free and the fields went back to their owners.
So of course you would do anything you needed to do to
do that on שבת. Shabbos Okay, so I could not have applied
it of all the different things that you got that sense of
the weightiness to do it on שבת. Shabbos I think these last
two probably speak to us more than some of the other ones.
Anyway, so it has to say by every individual thing. So that's
the גמרא's Gemara point that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer does not apply
universally, he needs a separate פסוק, pasuk, but he does exclude a
few things that you don't have a פסוק pasuk for. Of course,
since the גמרא Gemara gave the reason to exclude ציצית ומזוזה, tzitzis
u-mezuzah, you could have said the other thing and תוספות Tosafos asks,
why didn't you say he does apply it universally, but he excludes
ציצית ומזוזה tzitzis u-mezuzah that there's a specific reason that they're not
of the same nature of all of these, either they're more circumstantial
or the first reason which אביי rejected but to me it resonates
more which is that these other things are specific about a particular
day and therefore they get done regardless. But the big jump of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, also is moving from something like מילה וקרבנות
milah u-korbanos where the act itself overrides שבת Shabbos and therefore it
makes sense that the preparations can override שבת Shabbos? to even things
like שופר, סוכה, לולב shofar, sukkah, lulav where the act does not
require any override and nevertheless you can override שבת Shabbos to do
the preparations in order to do the act according to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer which we don't rule like. Let's just read a little
bit more now and get this into מילה. milah. We'll start the
next עמוד. מילה וכל מכשיריה דוחים את השבת דברי רבי אליעזר. Milah
ve-chol machshireha dochin et ha-shabbat divrei Rabbi Eliezer. מנא ליה לרבי אליעזר
הא? Mena lei le-Rabbi Eliezer ha? Finally we got had all the
other מצוות, mitzvos, let's get back to מילה. milah How does he
know that מילה milah overrides or the preparations of מילה milah, override
שבת? Shabbos. So אי מכולהו, ei mikul-hu, if it's from all the
other things we said, גמר כדאמרינן, gemar ked-amrinan, so like we said
reasons that all those other things had unique ways which is not
true by מילה, milah does not have the same weight as all
those other things. Although it is interesting the idea of night and
daytime, although מילה begins on day eight it might continue after day
eight even in nighttime as well, but okay. And anyway here's what
you could have to say you can't learn it from the other
cases: מה להנך שכן אם עבר זמנה בטלה. mah le-hanach she-ken im
avar zemana batlah.
All those other things, again this sense of the urgency of doing
it today, if you miss today you blew the מצוה. mitzvah. Even
if you sit in a סוכה sukkah the next day you didn't
do the סוכה sukkah the day before. אלא but here if you
didn't do ברית מילה bris milah, on the eighth day it's the
same ברית מילה, bris milah it's so you did it a day
later but it's the same מצוה mitzvah done at a different time,
whereas in all these other cases if you didn't do it at
that day on שבת Shabbos. you wouldn't have done it at all.
Here you will do it on a different day so do it
later, which makes a lot of sense, right? I think Rifky you
asked this when we first began, do it, do ברית מילה bris
milah the next day, so you don't do it on the eighth
day.
אלא distinction so you do it next day,
so look the ברית מילה bris milah I mean was was not
a right thing that you weren't circumcised on the eighth
day and you could never... right so that's the first... so that's
the thing. I mean you're stuck with the ברית מילה bris milah
for the rest of your life is that what you're saying if
you do it next day?
Yeah so same with סוכה. sukkah.
No but סוכה sukkah if you didn't do it today then you
totally did not do the מצוה. mitzvah. סוכה sukkah every separate day
is a separate מצוה. mitzvah. So I only sat in the סוכה
sukkah six days this year, not seven days this year, right? Whereas
the ברית מילה bris milah right I did the מצוה ברית מילה
mitzvah bris milah there's only one מצוה mitzvah only one checkmark. By
סוכה sukkah I had seven checkmarks and I only got six. I
just handed, I handed in the assignment late as opposed to not
handing in the assignment. Okay so you missed it. I know well
that's why the גמרא says ציצית tzitzis is only different because of
because it's circumstantial as opposed to these other things you know only
it's it's not as opposed to these things which are... ציצית tzitzis
is only if you happen to own the garment that's the way
the גמרא just distinguished it.
Well and מזוזה mezuzah is where you live.
Yeah but you don't have to own a house if you don't
own a house.
Even if you don't own it you have to do the מצוה.
mitzvah.
No but if you rent but that's probably only דרבנן de-rabbanan and
if
you don't have a house no but you don't it's still based
on the circumstances you find. True well yeah only if you own
it. But anyway it's still based on circumstances. Let's see what the
גמרא's answer is. So ברית מילה bris milah therefore as opposed to
these other things which is you like you know didn't as I
said there there you didn't get the checkmark for that thing itself,
here you hand it in, you hand in your assignment just a
day late so maybe that should not override שבת. Shabbos אלא היינו
טעמא דרבי אליעזר, Ela hainu ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer, here's the reasoning of
רבי אליעזר, דאמר קרא, d-amar kra, וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו. u-vayom
ha-shmini yimmol besar orlato.
Again he focuses on ביום bayom tells me even on שבת. Shabbos.
ואפילו בשבת. ve-afilu be-shabbat.
Now of course the first thing it has to tell me is
that ברית מילה bris milah itself overrides שבת Shabbos before it tells
me that the
מכשירין machshirin override שבת. Shabbos. So רש"י Rashi points out that later
we're going to say the idea that ברית מילה bris milah itself
overrides שבת Shabbos is a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. So
the extra ביום bayom here for him tells me that even the
מכשירין machshirin override שבת. Shabbos וליכתוב רחמנא במילי ולא לינסו הני ולגמר
מיניה? ve-lichtov rachmana be-milei ve-la linsov hanei u-ligmar mineih?
Back to the old thing, why not write by ברית מילה bris
milah and then apply it everywhere else? No. משום דאיכא למפרך, mishum
d-ika le-mifrach, מה למילה שכן נכרתו עליה שלש עשרה בריתות. mah le-milah
she-ken nichretu aleiha shelosh esreh britos.
By ברית מילה bris milah, it says ברית, ברית, ברית bris, bris,
bris thirteen times by אברהם Avraham when he's given the מצוה mitzvah
of ברית מילה, Bris Milah so therefore it has particular weight, so
that to be done on שבת Shabbos. and for its preparations to
be done on שבת Shabbos, is one thing, you could not have
applied it elsewhere. So basically the upshot of all of this is
is that רבי אליעזר applies it pretty universally even by things that
they themselves cannot be done on שבת. Shabbos If you need to
and the preparations they are, with the only things he excludes is
ציצית ומזוזה, tzitzis u-mezuzah, either because it's not specific to today there's
no weight weighted you know no particular weight of today which is
the first answer or because they're more circumstantial. And finally we get
to ברית מילה Bris Milah where he also applies it, even though
ברית מילה is one מצוה Mitzvah and could be done later, since
there's an idea of doing it on the eighth day, and on
the eighth day is so important that overrides שבת, even the מכשירין
Machshirin override שבת as well, so we will continue with this and
with his debate with the חכמים Chachamim tomorrow.